Stanford University, Honors Program in Latin American Studies, Theses SC4-4257
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Honors Program in Latin American Studies, theses
1975-2011
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Center for Latin American Studies
SC4-4257
6.75 Linear Feet (134 volumes in 14 boxes)
The collection consists of Latin American Studies honors theses written by Stanford University undergraduates.
Information about Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. No photocopies may be made.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of Latin American Studies honors theses written by Stanford University undergraduates.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred to the Stanford University Archives by the center for Latin American Studies in August 2010. Additional theses were transferred from the Hume Writing Center in 2011.
Student papers.; Latin America; Stanford University. Center for Latin American Studies
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2010-086
  - Aguirre, Javier Mendoza, Mexico City: The Road to Democracy., 1996 (Box 5)
  - Badger, Rodney S., Health Care in Brazil: A Qualitative Study of Government and Private Medicine in Londrina, Parana., 1975 (Box 1)
  - Barbosa, Ines, International Organizations, the State and Non=Governmental Organization Working with Street Children: The Case of Lima, Peru., 1998 (Box 6)
  - Bassis, Betsy, Civil Society in the Fight Against Corruption in New Democracies: The Case of Argentina., 1994 (Box 5)
  - Baum, Geoffrey, The Mexican Textile Industry in the Economic Crisis: Who paid for the Adjustment?., 1990 (Box 3)
  - Beck, Catherine, The Converted Mission: The Radicalization of Catholic Missionaries in Brazil., 1984 (Box 3)
  - Biery, Heather Marie, Many-sided Truths, Many-Sided Images: Chiapan Photographer's Struggle for Self-Representation., 1999 (Box 7)
  - Bilderbeck, John A., Talkin' Bout My Generation: Attitudes of Chilean University Students Toward Political Participation., 2001 (Box 8)
  - Bird, Brian, An Examination of Mexican States' Corruption Levels and their Ties to Political Parties., 2003 (Box 10)
  - Bird, Lola E., The Poplular Church in Azuay, Ecuador: A Case Study of Its Socio-political Effects., 1993 (Box 4)
  - Blom, Dominique, Building Houses, Constructing Identity: Gender, Politics and Self-Help Projects in Santiago de Chile., 1993 (Box 4)
  - Boas, Taylor C., www.cubalibre.cu? Transnational Networking and the Impact of the Internet on Non-Democratic Rule., 1999 (Box 7)
  - Boyer, David J., Free-Market Reform and its Implications on Deforestation and Urbanization in Chile: The Environmental Impact of Neoliberal Policies in Chile., 1996 (Box 5)
  - Brian, Rebecca M., Beyond Pursuit of the Neoliberal Ideal: The Reforms and Reorientation of Chilean Economic Policy, 1973-1997. (Box 6)
  - Brunette, Rachel, Dekasegi Nikkeijin: Refelections on Japanese Immigration Policy and the Return Migration of Japanese Latin Americans., 1999 (Box 12)
  - Burns, Janifer, Migration and Land Tenure in Tabasco, Mexico., 1978 (Box 2)
  - Calvin, Linda Sue, Education Reform in Rural Peru., 1975 (Box 1)
  - Charo, Lisa, Do Cultural Barriers Limit Screening for Cervical Cancer Among Latino Women in East Palo Alto?. (Box 8)
  - Chavez, Rebecca, The Nexus between Nixinger, the CIA, and ITT: Ending Allende's "Chile for Chileans., 1999 (Box 7)
  - Conte, Elena, Reversing Language Shift: Intercultural Bilingual Education and the Mapuche Movement in Chile., 2001 (Box 8)
  - Corey-Moran, Nat, The Language of Rain in the Land of Clouds: Language, Community and Change in San Miguel el Grande, Oaxaca., 2003 (Box 10)
  - Courtney, Mary Michele, Creating and Mainting a Dependency: Temporrary Labor from Mexico to the United States., 1986 (Box 3)
  - Dang, Nga, San Pablo de Amali, Ecuador: A Case Study of the Power between Land-Lwning and Landless Women., 1990 (Box 3)
  - Early, Stephanie Margaret, Cuba's Son: The Elian Gonzalez Case and the Complexity of US-Cuba Storytelling., 2005 (Box 10)
  - Eischeid, Keith Michael, Trial and Error: Case Study Analyses of the Environmental Impact of Neoliberal Policies in Chile., 1996 (Box 5)
  - Engel Wells, Kelly, Breaking Camp: A Needs Analysis and Policy Recommendations for Colombian Refugee Women in Ibarra, Ecuador., 2005 (Box 10)
  - Farrell, Leanne, Gas por Desarrollo' in the Bolivian Iowlands: Towards participatory compensation and indigenous rural development along the Bolivia-Brazil and Cuiaba natural gas pipelines., 2001-02 (Box 9)
  - Fisher, Andrew, The Aylwin Administration and the Legacy of Human Rights Violations: The Search for a Centrist Path to Resolution., 1992 (Box 3)
  - Fisher, Michael, Economic Policy and Political Instability: Cotton Textile Investment in Brazil, 1925-1937., 1992 (Box 3)
  - Franz, Michael A., A Structure of Contradiction: Unaccompanied Minors in INS Custody in South Texas., 1993 (Box 4)
  - Fudem, Gary, Cross-Cultural Living and Working: The Effects of North American Volunteers and Latin American Hosts..., 1977-78 (Box 1)
  - Galeana, Fernando, Explaining the Demand for Land Titling in Mexico: Credit and Urbanization in the Ejido Sector. (Box 9)
  - Garcoa, Bernabe N.C., Jr., Description of Possible Earthquake Damage at Archaeologic Site of Tulum in Quitana Roo, Mexico., 2001-02 (Box 9)
  - Garrot, Luke J., The Mexican Independent Left: A Study of Dynamic Deradicaliation-Orienting its Future and Tracing the Past., 1988 (Box 3)
  - Glick, Andrew J., Socioeconomic Factors and Childhood Diarrhea in Panama., 1980 (Box 2)
  - Gomez, Michael, Industrial Diversification as a Strategy for Dependence Management: Venezuela Since 1958., 1978 (Box 2)
  - Gonzalez-Ponciano,Jorge Ramon, "Esas Sangres No Estan Limpias" El Racismo, El Estado y La Nacion en Guatemala (1944-1997). (Box 12)
  - Gonzalez, Ana, "El Voto de Castigo:" Analyzing Democratic Transitions: A Case Study of Jocotepec, Jalisco, Mexico., 1995 (Box 5)
  - Gonzalez, Xochiqnetzal, Indigenous Autonomy and the Nation: the conflicts of imaginary and physical concepts as illustrated by four pueblos indigena's struggles in Mexico-breaking free from ideological domination; understanding, legitimizing, and exercising Indigenous cosmovisions., 2000-01 (Box 8)
  - Gorin, Linda, Stuttering in Lima, Peru: A Qualitative Case Study of Current Concepts, Theories and Treatment Facilities., 1977 (Box 2)
  - Gossack, Linda, Argentine University Students and Peron (1946-1955)., 1977 (Box 1)
  - Gundling, Daniela, In the Footsetpes of Small Farmers in Rio Grande de Sol: Making Sustainable Rural Development a Reality., 2003 (Box 10)
  - Harrison, Shauna, The Exportation of Unhealthy Ideals: The Influence of American Culture on Body Image in Costa Rica., 2000 (Box 7)
  - Heineman, Monique, Extending Life in Chile: CONASIDA's HIV and AIDS Bitherapy Program., 1999 (Box 8)
  - Herring, Christy, The Culture of Test-Taking in a Bilingual Classroom: An Ethnographic Approach., 1997 (Box 6)
  - Hiller, Laurie, Peru's Reactions to the Falkland/Malvinas War., 1983 (Box 3)
  - Himan, Megan, The Political and Economic Reintegration of Nicaraguan Exiles., 1997 (Box 6)
  - Hornbeak, Dana Marie, Voices of Change: Public-Private Collaborations Providing Health and Social Services in Rural Latin America: A Case Study in Pucallpa, Peru., 2005 (Box 10)
  - Jack, Robert, Truth on the Path, Verdad Sobre el Camino: An Analysis and Anthology of Young Writers in Contemporary Nicaragua., 2003 (Box 10)
  - Jackson, Derek D., Interfamilial OVP3 Transmission in Mexico and its Implications for the Polio Immunization Endgame in the Developing World., 2003 (Box 10)
  - James, Ken, Christian Base Communities in El Salvador and Nicaragua., 1990 (Box 3)
  - Jenkins, Jessica Marie, Whose Liberation? Women and Progressive Catholicism in Post-War El Salvador., 2003 (Box 10)
  - Jerome, Jean, Agrarian Reform and the Transfer of Power on Peru's Sugar Plantations, 1968-1974. (Box 2)
  - Jimenez, Alfredo, Popular Theater in Mexico., 1977 (Box 2)
  - Jones, Royce, A Preliminary Investigation of Selected Hot Springs in Southern Peru and Their Potential as a Geothermal Energy Source., 1980 (Box 3)
  - Kangaygia, Admas, Brazil's Foreign Policy in Africa: An Evolution Towards South-South Cooperation. (Box 8)
  - Keller, Mckenna, No Longer Will We Live on Bended Knees: The Zapatista Approach to Resistance in the 1990s., 1999 (Box 7)
  - Kendall, Megan, A Whale in a Swimming Pool: High Technology as a Strategy for National Development in Costa Rica., 2001-02 (Box 9)
  - Kinnamon, Daniel D., Assessing the World Bank: An Analysis of the World Bank Based on my Service Internship Experience., 2001-02 (Box 9)
  - Kos-Read, Isaac, Information and Communication Technology Implementation: A case-study of Enlaces and nine secondary schools in the Metropolitan Region of Chile., 2000 (Box 7)
  - Kostohryz Vergara, James A., Capitalism, Democracy and the Economics of Political Democratization in Mexico., 1990-91 (Box 3)
  - Lobel, Meredith, A Historical Discussion of Colombian Population Policy., 1977 (Box 2)
  - Machin, Horacio, La transformacion del intelectual latinoamericano. Argentina 1985-1989., 1993 (Box 8)
  - Magarin, Luisa, Portraits of Change Women's lives over 60 years in a Mayan Town San Pedro, La Laguna, Guatemala., 2001 (Box 8)
  - Marietta, Amy, Laying the Foundation for Energy-Efficient Construction in Chile's Low-Income Housing: A Case Study in the Programa Vivienda Progresiva Privada Regarding Chile's New Reglamentacion Termica., 2001 (Box 8)
  - Maxfield, Marla M., The Legacy of North American Free Trade and Liberal Foreign Investment Policies: A Comparison of Hisotrical Policies: A Comparison of Historical Attempts at North American Economic Integration in Ligth of the Successful North American Free Trade Agreement., 1994 (Box 5)
  - McCotter, Sage, A Portrait of Instability: Obstacles to Lasting School Reform in Chile, 1964 to Present., 1996 (Box 5)
  - McKean, Cressida S., The Conservative Press in Chile: The Manipulation of an "Ideological Apparatus" by a Domestic and Foreign Opposition to Allende (1970-1973)., 1976 (Box 1)
  - McKee, Peggy, Community Development and Social Change Affecting Women: Agrarian Reform and Mother's Clubs in the Central Peruvian Highlands., 1985 (Box 3)
  - Miller, Stuart, Dollarization of Ecuador's Economy., 2001 (Box 8)
  - Mohr, Hope, Domestic Violence in Post-Revolutionary Nicaragua: The "Private" Side of the Transition to Democracy., 1994 (Box 5)
  - Moorehead, Elisabeth, Highland Inca Architecture in Adobe., 1975 (Box 1)
  - Moreno, Carleen E., Development in the Village of San Joaquin., 1989-90 (Box 3)
  - Morgan, Amanda Lynn, The State of Institutionalization of Women's Issues: A Case Study of Chile's SERNAM., 1996 (Box 11)
  - Muchnick, Adam E., Emerging Economic Policies of Chile's New Democracy: A Balanced Approach to Development., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Munoz, Eric, Center-Local Relations of Domination in a Unitary Republic: The Case of Chile, 1964-1992. (Box 4)
  - Musser, Lila, Combining Community with Conservation: The Private Nature Reserve in Chile and Costa Rica., 1998 (Box 6)
  - Nashashibi, Lola, The Role of Foreign Banks in the Development of Brazilian Agriculture., 1978 (Box 2)
  - Nichols, Christopher M., Pluralistic Medicine in Zinacantan, A Mayan Community in Mexico., 1988 (Box 4)
  - Nixon, J. Alexander, Profiting off the Landscape: A Hisotry of Cuban Environmental Policy., 2000 (Box 7)
  - Ortega-Operchunck, Nica D., Soy Mexicana de este Lado: An Examination of Female Mexican Immigrant Identity., 1998 (Box 6)
  - Pacheco,John Anthony, Disease and Illness Among Chamula Children-a medical systems analysis in a Maya community of southeastern Mexico., 1989 (Box 4)
  - Padilla, Julie A., Mexico City's Nueva Cancion: Lo personal es politico., 1990 (Box 4)
  - Parker, Molly, Understanding Cultural Appropriateness: The Case of Family Planning Classes for Latinas., 1996 (Box 5)
  - Pasos, Maria, Chile's Sweet and Sour Liberalization under Pinochet., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Peltz, Maxwell, Costa Rica and the Reagan Administration: Sparring with a Giant., 1989 (Box 4)
  - Pineda, Carlos V., Turtles, Trees and Tourism: Conservation, development and local participation in Barra de Tortuguero, Costa Rica., 1992-93 (Box 4)
  - Polityka, Catherine, The Lack of Adequate Water Supply and Sanitation in the Favelas of Sao Paulo, Brazil: Constraining Factors and Recommended Solutions., 1998 (Box 12)
  - Pressman, Lauren Nicole, The Privatization of The Argentine Telecommunications Industry., 1995 (Box 5)
  - Radkakrishna, Rohan, In Search of Kume Mongnen: The Integration of Indigenous Mapuche Medicine and Biomedicine in Central Chile- An Ethnographic Case Study of Hospital Makewe's Complementary Health Model., 2001-02 (Box 9)
  - Redhage, Jill Elizabeth, On Reforming the Ecuadorian Judicial System: Praises and Problems., 2003 (Box 10)
  - Reynolds, James M., The Politics of Socialism in Authoritarian Chile., 1992 (Box 4)
  - Rico, Rita, Race and Gender in Revolutionary Cuba: An Analysis of Rhetoric and Testimony., 2001-02 (Box 9)
  - Rodriguez, Lauren, Decentralization and Implications for NGOs in Sexual and Reproductive Health., 2005 (Box 11)
  - Rogers, Louise, The Collapse of the Amazon Rubber Boom., 1977 (Box 1)
  - Rutner, Linda, Jorge Amado: Portrayal of Brazilian Society., 1979 (Box 2)
  - Ruvolo, Julie, The Performance of Tradition in Mangueira Samba School: An enduring identity in flux in today's Cariocan Carnaval parade., 2004 (Box 12)
  - Salinas, Nereyda, The Decentralization and Privatization Educational Reforms Implemented in Chile in the 1980s., 1996 (Box 11)
  - Sandoval, Maria Bernadette, PRONASOL: Mexico's National Solidarity Program., 1992-93 (Box 4)
  - Schuster, Caroline, Land, Credit, Identity: The Politics of Microfinance in Argentina's Altiplano., 2005 (Box 11)
  - Sekaquaptewa, Kimball, Chile, Chilean and their Culture: A review., 1996 (Box 6)
  - Serwer, Karen, Despierta Mi Cuerpo--Negociacion entre la Transgresion y el Silencio: Un Esudio de Cuatro Mujeres Poetas Ecuatorianas., 1997 (Box 6)
  - Siebel, Jennifer Lynn, Conservation versus Development: A North American in Southern Chile., 1996 (Box 6)
  - Skeen, William F., Equal Opportunity in the Cuban Revolution., 1976 (Box 1)
  - Slesar, Kristen, Disappear: The History and Psychology of Disappearance in Chile, 1973-present., 2001 (Box 8)
  - Smith, Mariama, Afro-Argentines: Assimilation as a Response to Racism., 1995 (Box 5)
  - Solomon-Oyarce, Lorna Cameron, La Historia de Tantas Marias - The Story of the Transnational Mother., 2002 (Box 11)
  - Solomon, Margaret, Intersections of Class and Gender: Feminist and Popular Organizations in Mexico City., 1993 (Box 5)
  - Stricklin, Susan, An Indian Boarding School in Highland Chiapas, Mexico., 1977 (Box 1)
  - Swift Koller, Theadora, The Tango Chronicles., 1999 (Box 7)
  - Thrupp, Lori, Deforestation, Agricultural Development, and Cattle Expansion in Costa Rica., 1980 (Box 4)
  - Tuschman, Avi Samuel, The Potato Goblin Irony and Taboo in the Northern Ecuadorian Highland Quechua Joke-Narrative: A Contribution to the Anthropology of Humor., 2001-02 (Box 12)
  - Van Valkenburg, David, Some Features of Belize Creole., 1976 (Box 1)
  - Varia, Nisha, "Invisible" Work or Eyes That Don't See? Ninas Trabajadoras in Guadalajara, Mexico., 1996-97 (Box 12)
  - Vaughn, Rubiahna Leye, "Yo tengo que luchar": Narratives of Women int eh Afro-Ecuadorian Civil Rights Movement., 2005 (Box 11)
  - Weisser, Lynn, Street Children: Programs for Gamines in Bogota, Colombia., 1979 (Box 2)
  - Welch, Antonia, Sex and the Street: A Study of Reproductive Health Among Street Girls in Quito, Ecuador., 1999-00 (Box 9)
  - Welsh, Richard Osbourne, Taking the Leap: Latin American Societies, Policies, and Economic Growth., 2007 (Box 11)
  - Wernecke, William, The Mixed Corporation Model in Brazil: A Case Analysis of Three State Steel Firms 1964-1976. (Box 1)
  - Wiatt, Katherine, Revolucao Humana: Stories of Struggle and Human Transformation Within the Movimento Sem Terra., 2000 (Box 8)
  - Wiener, Jocelyn, Dejame Respirar: Peace and Gang Violence in El Salvador., 1999 (Box 6)
  - Williams, Manley, Popular Organizations and the Church in Brazil since the 'Abertura'., 1987 (Box 4)
  - Yackovlev, Irene, The Alliance of Elites and the Success of Macroeconomic Stabilization and Structural Adjustment: a Case Study of Venezuela., 1996 (Box 7)
  - Yandell, John, "The Struggle for Gay Unions: A Comparative Case Study of Gay Unions in Argentina and Chile". (Box 9)
  - Yates-Doerr, Emily, Weaving an Identity: Cultural Change and Traditional Dress in Todos Santos, Guatemala., 2001 (Box 8)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2011-152
  - Crocker, Rebecca Masten, Children in crisis: Mexico's internal migration and its effects on child poverty in the Yucatán., 1994 (Box 1)
  - Hwang, Theresa Y., Partnerships for social change: HIV, Umbanda and healing in Brazil., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Kendall, Megan, A whale in a swimming pool: high technology as a strategy for national development in Costa Rica., 2002 (Box 1)
  - Palazzo, Nicolas, Pension reform in Argentina: the politics of conflict, compensation, and compromise., 2007 (Box 1)
  - Stewart, Douglas, Sandman: an ethnoecological analysis of colonists and deforestation on the Transamazon Highway., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Walseth, Megan D., Reconstructive remembering: truth commissions and democracy in Chile and El Salvador., 1997 (Box 1)
  - Skinner, Sara Justine, Young, poor, and Brazilian: HIV prevention, identity and solidarity in the inner city., 1995 (Box 1)
  - Leib, Sean, Literature of the Diaspora: political exile and southern cone literature of the 1970s and 1980s., 1993 (Box 1)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2018-060
  - Zaffaroni, Charles A. A., "Integrated water resource management and Chilean private water markets in the context of growing scarcity and climate change", 2011 May 25 (Box 1)